只有一种生物为了自己的生存
Only one creature has carved a life for itself
在地球的每一个角落都留下了印迹
in every habitat on earth.
那就是人类
That creature is us.
天地悠悠
All over the world,
我们仍依靠创造力来努力存活于世
we still use our ingenuity to survive in the wild places,
远离文明开化的城市
far from the city lights,
直面原始险恶的自然
face to face with raw nature.
草本植物是一类非凡的植物
Grass is a remarkable plant.
它供养着不计其数的生命
It supports a great abundance of life.
小麦  水稻  大麦和玉米
Wheat, rice, barley and corn,
这些都属于草本植物
they're all grasses and they feed us,
它们是我们的主要粮食
and the grasslands feed the animals
并养育着供人类食用的动物们
that feed our world too.
我们在草原上的活动改变了地貌
Our lives on the grasslands have transformed the planet,
从美国辽阔的牧场
from the prairies of America
到中国的梯田
to the rice terraces of China.
但这绝非易事
But it's not been easy.
人类绞尽脑汁  鼓足勇气
It's taken every last ounce of human courage and ingenuity
才成为草原的统领
to become masters of the grasslands.
草原
力量之源
肯尼亚南部的大草原晨光微曦
Dawn on the Savannah in southern Kenya.
拉基塔和伙伴们已经等候多时
It's the moment Rakita and his mates have been waiting for.
长途迁徙的牛羚群终于到达
The wildebeest migration has arrived.
这里丰盈的水草
Here, lush grasses support
养育着世间最庞大的牧群
the largest herds of animals in the world.
这正是多罗博猎人们捕猎的好时机
A bounty of opportunity for these Dorobo hunters.
但要想获得这些待人宰割的猎物
But there's fierce competition for all this meat on the hoof
他们得和世间最高效的
from some of the world's
猎食动物展开残酷竞争
most efficient killers.
渺小的人类  没有獠牙和厉爪
So how do mere humans, without fangs or claws,
速度又远不及牛羚
who can't outrun a wildebeest,
要怎样才能分到一杯羹呢
get a meal around here?
拉基塔靠的是大脑和团队合作
Rakita uses brains and teamwork.
他要先让狮子们完成对牛羚的捕杀
His plan is to let the lions kill the wildebeest,
然后从它们眼皮底下把猎物偷走
then he'll steal their dinner from right under their noses.
他的两个朋友必不可少
His two friends are essential.
狮群可不会轻易被吓退
Lions aren't easily intimidated.
首先  拉基塔必须找到
First, Rakita must find
雄狮拖走尸体的踪迹
the tracks of a lion pride on the hunt.
沿着这条路走
65岁的拉基塔经验丰富  由他带头跟踪
At 65, he's a veteran hunter and takes the lead.
他们必须加倍小心
They must watch their backs -
因为他们已踏入食人猛兽的领地
this is man-eater territory.
豺狼在嚎叫...
因为狮群就在附近
所有迹象表明附近一场杀戮刚刚结束
All the signs point to a fresh kill nearby.
你觉得它们在这吗
是的  我能看到它们了  就在那
拉基塔曾被狮群袭击过
Rakita's been attacked by lions before.
他知道后果不堪设想
He knows this could end badly.
这种时候你只感觉浑身紧绷...
...心怦怦作响
他们面对的是15只饥肠辘辘的狮子
They're up against 15 hungry lions,
但如果他们齐心合力
but, if they act as one,
他们就可能把狮群
they might just intimidate the lions
从猎物的尸体边吓走
and push them off their kill.
他们行动了
They make their move.
自信是最重要的部分
Self-confidence is everything.
这是一场终极的对峙
This is the ultimate face-off.
突然间  狮群退却了
Suddenly, the lions back off.
在狮子意识到这只是虚张声势之前
Rakita has just minutes
拉基塔只有几分钟的时间
before the lions realise it's a bluff.
大约几秒钟以后
In a matter of seconds,
他割下了牛羚的一条大腿
he butchers the haunch of the wildebeest,
然后他们迅速地撤离了
and they beat a hasty retreat.
直到你偷到了食物...
而且没有人受伤...
...你才能够放松下来
...并为此感到愉快
这是人类自古以来
This is a scene which has played out
以弱胜强的真实写照
throughout human existence,
捕猎时他们用的是脑子而非蛮力
hunters using brains, not brawn,
从而智取他们强大的对手
to outwit their mighty competitors.
我们着实打劫了狮子们一把
你觉得那有多少只狮子呢
十五只或者更多吧
但不是每个人都敢与狮子对抗...
...有些人就是怕死的懦夫
挂着的肉让洞穴更有家的气息了
利用别的动物来为你捕猎的确高明
Getting another animal to do the killing for you is clever,
但亲自操刀捕猎则是更大的挑战
but making the kill yourself is an even bigger challenge.
在非洲大陆的另一端
At the other end of Africa,
在喀拉哈里沙漠的边缘
on the edge of the Kalahari Desert,
有一片更为干燥的草原
lies a much drier grassland,
这里的动物要稀少得多
supporting far fewer animals.
这儿可没有免费的午餐
There's no free lunch here.
昆和纳奥是永豪西族[音译]布须曼人
!Kun and N//ao are Ju/'hoansi bushmen.
昆是猎手头领
!Kun is a master hunter,
他是永豪西族人中少数几个
one of a handful of Ju'hoansi
依然掌握着捕猎大猎物的本领的人
who still have the skills to hunt big game.
昆在指导他的徒弟
So !Kun is teaching his apprentice
让这种宝贵的技能得以流传
to keep this precious knowledge alive.
这场捕猎开始于生一把大火
The hunt begins by kindling fire.
他们把唯一的泉眼周围
They burn the grass from around
几公里的草木全部烧掉
the only waterhole for many kilometres.
他们知道动物们最终会来这里找水喝
They know the animals will ultimately come to drink here
等到那时
and when they do,
它们便无处藏身
they'll have nowhere to hide.
他们的弓箭太小  无法一击致命
Their bows and dart arrows are too small to kill outright,
所以他们改良了武器
so they refine their weapons.
猎手头领昆很清楚去哪里寻找毒药
!Kun, the master, knows exactly where to find poison.
在这板结的沙土里有种甲虫的幼虫
Within this hardened sand shell is a beetle grub.
只要一滴虫汁渗入哪怕最微小的伤口
If just one drop of beetle juice gets into the tiniest cut,
也会令其一命呜呼
it will kill him.
他小心翼翼地把它涂在箭尖
He anoints his arrows with great care.
但他们的猎物同样狡猾
But their prey are wily too,
于是他们搭了一个草棚
so they build a grass hide.
在那里设下埋伏
This is an ambush.
昆希望他的徒弟能抓住
!Kun wants his apprentice
属于自己的第一只羚羊
to get his first kudu.
看来它们在来了
走近了吗
这种羚羊有着敏锐的听觉和锐利的眼睛
The antelope's acute hearing and sharp eyes
意味着他必须悄无声息且不能被看见
mean he must learn to move silently and without being seen.
可是纳奥还是暴露了
But N//ao has been spotted.
机会失之交臂
The moment is lost.
你得边看边学
条纹羚诡计多端
...你不能让它看到你的脸
两天过后
Two days later,
这两个布须曼人还潜伏在那里
the bushmen are still in their hide,
等待羚羊们的干渴战胜恐惧
hoping that the kudus' thirst will overcome their fear.
可它们却迟迟不来
But they stay away.
连头领也措手不及的是
Then even the master is caught unprepared.
一只美洲豹突然出现
It's a leopard.
猛然间猎手变成猎物
Suddenly the hunters risk becoming the hunted.
美洲豹的咬合力足以嚼碎人类的脑壳
A leopard's jaws have the power to crush a human skull.
他们不停地祈祷猎豹没有看到他们
They're praying the leopard hasn't seen them.
纳奥趴在阴影里
N//ao lies low in the shadows.
这次他们终于没被发现
This time they've managed to remain undetected.
今天是潜伏的第六天了
It's day six in the hide,
徒弟至今无法靠近他的猎物
and the apprentice is no closer to getting a meal.
又一群条纹羚来了
A new group of kudu come in.
他们抓住这次机会
They've got one chance.
两个人都上满了弓
Both men raise their bows.
正中靶心
Bull's-eye!
一发中的  羚羊纷纷四散逃开
An arrow has hit home and the kudu scatter.
射得漂亮
我的天呐  确实射得非常准
受伤的条纹羚会带着毒箭
The injured kudu will run for many kilometres
继续奔跑出好几公里
with the poison arrow in its flank,
毒素在它体内缓慢地产生作用
as the toxins slowly take effect.
追逐就此开始
The pursuit begins.
首先他们要找到箭杆
First, they must find the arrow shaft.
它能指示出追踪的方向
It will show them which tracks to follow
并能确定是谁射中了猎物
and also who made the hit.
找到箭杆了
这是你的箭
是的  就是你的
你射中了你的第一支条纹羚  太棒了
希望毒药能有作用
会有用的
它好像往那个方向跑了
从现在开始  剩下的就只有追寻了
From here on, it's all about tracking.
地面上羚羊的脚印纵横交错
The ground is criss-crossed with hoof prints.
走错方向意味着一切将徒劳无功
The wrong decision will mean a wild-goose chase.
看  它在这撒了泡尿
能看得出来  毒素在起作用了
我们肯定能杀了那只羚羊
追寻途中
While tracking,
猎人们通过察看猎物留下的痕迹
the hunters look at the landscape
一路追踪着猎物
through the eyes of their prey.
十小时后  他们终于赶上了那只羚羊
After ten hours, they finally catch up with the kudu.
毒素让它变得虚弱了
The poison has weakened it.
它已经筋疲力尽  几近死亡
She's exhausted, near death.
纳奥将矛扎进它的心脏
N//ao aims a spear to the heart
迅速地结果了它
to deliver a swift end.
七天后
After seven days,
纳奥最终杀了他的第一只羚羊
N//ao has finally killed his first kudu.
现在世间又多了一个能做到这个的人了
Now there is one more person in the world who can do this.
他们搬回去的肉将能养活整个村子
The meat they'll carry home will feed their whole village.
且这只动物的每个部位都会被利用起来
And every part of the animal will be put to use.
这片焦土看似死地
This burnt landscape looks dead,
但野草的生命力是难以置信的顽强
but grass is incredibly resilient.
下第一场雨的时候  草又再生了
With the first drops of rain, it regenerates.
在雨水泛滥成河泽的地方
And where these rains become floods,
草长的速度和水位上升并驾齐驱
grass grows to keep pace with the rising waters.
在世界各地
Around the world,
有很多草原经历着如此极端的季节变化
many grasslands undergo such extreme seasonal changes,
这带来新的机遇
bringing new opportunities,
也暗藏着危险
but also lurking dangers.
在柬埔寨
In Cambodia,
洞里萨湖周围的草原成为泽国
the grasslands around Tonle Sap lake are flooding...
在短短的几周内
...and for a few short weeks
那儿的猎物垂手可得
there are rich pickings to be had.
这是瓦纳大捞一笔的好机会
It's Vaana's big chance to make a killing.
他来这里捕猎一种无法预料的
He's here to hunt an unexpected,
隐秘并且可能置人于死地的野生猛兽
hidden and potentially fatal wild prey.
我在小船上的时候
...想知道黑色的水里有什么
...我很为我的孩子担心
瓦纳的捕猎技术在于识别
Vaana's hunting skill lies in recognising
普通的和危险的猎物
the difference between an easy meal and a deadly catch.
但是他寻找的不是鱼
But it's not fish he's after.
而是蛇
It's snakes.
在这片水草地里有无数条蛇
There are many millions of them in this flooded grassland.
绝大部分是可食用的水蛇
Most are edible water snakes
但是却是毒蛇
but some are venomous.
如果抓起来的是条眼镜蛇
If he pulls up a cobra,
那他就可能会被咬死
its bite could kill him.
这就像一场俄罗斯轮盘游戏
It's a game of Russian roulette.
连他五岁的儿子都必须成为蛇类专家
Even his five-year-old son has to be a snake expert,
能准确识别蛇的种类才可以在这里生存
knowing which is which means survival here.
蛇在这里大量聚集
The snakes gather in these huge numbers
去追捕那些在水草中产卵的鱼
to hunt the fish which spawn in the submerged grass.
没时间讲卫生了
It's no time to be squeamish.
每跑掉一条都是瓦纳的损失
Every escapee sees Vaana's profits slither away.
我们今天抓了很多蛇
瓦纳的整个家庭都得设法对付蛇
Vaana's whole family must get to grips with snakes.
给这女儿一条活蛇玩玩
对孩子们来说
For the kids,
它们是很受欢迎的新玩具
they are welcome new toys.
爸爸  我可以再要一条吗
妈妈  看  它咬了我的脚
不  它正盯着你的蛋蛋
它正盯着你的蛋蛋
它正想进那里去
瓦纳捕的蛇就是卖到
Vaana's catch is destined
这个世界上最大的蛇类市场
for the biggest snake market in the world.
几周内有超过六百万条蛇在这里转手
Over 6 million snakes change hands in a matter of weeks.
我想卖每公斤五千瑞尔[约人民币8元]
四千怎么样
好吧  四千瑞尔全拿走
他跟蛇斗争一周的报酬
His payment for a week's snake wrangling...
注: 1英镑=100便士  约为6540柬埔寨瑞尔
60便士
60p.
别数了  把它放好
但在草原生存靠的不仅仅是捕猎
But survival in the grasslands isn't all about hunting.
在东非  马塞族人
In East Africa, the Masai
已经学会了怎样同一种野生鸟合作
have learnt how to collaborate with a wild bird
只有通过合作他们才能吃到一种甜点
to get a sweet treat they can only get if they work together.
莱塔托正在用哨声吸引一只向蜜鸟
Leitato is whistling to attract a honey guide.
这种鸟正如其名
It's a bird that is aptly named.
向蜜鸟用它仅对人会才发出的叫声
The honey guide answers their whistles
回应了他们的哨声
with a call it only uses to talk to humans.
它在那儿  它在那儿
它一闻到他们所寻找的食物的味道
She starts a game of Follow My Leader...
就玩起了"学领袖"游戏[一种儿童游戏]
...since only she can smell the food they're after.
当它靠近目标的时候
When she's close to the prize,
就会改变叫声
she changes her call,
让人们知道快到了
letting them know they're getting hotter.
在这儿  哇
这下孩子们走运了  有一个蜂窝
The boys have hit the jackpot - a beehive.
向蜜鸟的任务完成了
The bird's job is done.
站在哪里最好呢
就是那儿
好吧  我们点堆火吧
现在他们开始履行交易中他们的部分
Now they have to fulfil their part of the bargain -
把蜂蜜弄出来
getting the honey out.
蜂蜜藏在树的深处
It's hidden deep in the tree
被几百只愤怒的非洲蜜蜂保护着
protected by hundreds of angry African bees.
他们用烟熏使蜂群平静下来
They use smoke to calm them.
但这并不能减轻被蜂蛰到的疼楚
But it doesn't make the stings any less painful.
我太小了  够不着
孩子们知道他们必须回馈向导
The boys know they have to pay their guide.
把蜂房和一些蜜蜂幼虫留给它
Honeycomb with added grubs.
真好吃  真甜
我们去哪里可以找到更多
真是完美的合作关系
It's the perfect partnership,
但是  每个马塞族男孩都知道
but, as every Masai boy knows,
要是你不给向蜜鸟报酬
if you don't give the honey guide its reward,
下次它就会把你带到狮子窝去
next time it will lead you to a lion's den!
我们已经学会如何在野生草原寻找食物
So we've learnt how to find food in the wild grasslands,
依靠自己
either on our own,
或者从其他生物那儿获得点帮助
or with a bit of help from others.
但在学会如何开发草原本身时
But our mastery of the grasslands took a huge leap forward
我们对草原的掌控又来了个大飞跃
when we learnt how to exploit the grass itself.
小麦  玉米和大米最初都是野草
Wheat, maize and rice all started life as wild grasses,
被我们培育成农作物
which we've bred into crops.
这让我们每年可以养活成千上万的人
This has enabled us to feed millions of people every year,
于是  我们在田地边安顿了下来
and so we've settled down and
建立起了家园
built homes beside our fields.
但这些人类创造的丰富产物
But this man-made abundance is irresistible
让被称为害虫的动物们欲罢不能
to many animals we now call pests.
在非洲平原
On the African plains
这些谷物杀手泛滥成灾
these cereal killers come in plague proportions.
艾什尔住在坦桑尼亚
Isiah lives in Tanzania.
他的大米就快收割了
His rice harvest is just days away,
但他知道一场虫灾即将来袭
but he knows an aerial attack is imminent.
它们三月会来
它们要吃  我也要吃  但它们会吃光一切
他必须警觉
He must be vigilant,
时刻密切关注他害怕听到的声音
ever alert to the sound he dreads.
首先听到的是噪音
The noise comes first...
然后是先头部队
...then the advance party...
后面跟着密密麻麻一大群
...followed by the swarm.
它们是奎利亚雀
They are quelea.
数以百万计地结伴飞来
They come in their millions
人们称之为"蝗鸟"
and people call them locust birds.
它们是地球上数量最多的鸟类
They are the most numerous bird species on Earth,
贪嗜谷物
ravenous for grain.
艾什尔和他的邻居们
Isiah and his neighbours
必须努力阻止它们停留
must try to prevent the quelea from settling,
否则鸟群会在一小时内吃光他们的谷物
otherwise the flock will strip their crop in an hour.
这场战争他是不可能胜利的
It's not a battle he can win,
他能做的只是尽量减少损失而已
it's about limiting his losses.
种子成熟的时候
As the seeds ripen,
这些迁徙的鸟群从来不会停在一个地方
these migrant flocks never stand still.
但它们有个致命弱点
But they do have an Achilles heel.
为了繁衍  它们必须停下来
In order to breed, the quelea must stop,
密密麻麻地编织无数的巢
weaving thousands of nests in tight colonies.
这是农民们报复的良机
This is the farmers' chance to strike back.
就在多数鸟都去觅食的时候
While most of the flock is away feeding,
他们放置了致命的陷阱
a deadly trap is laid.
黄昏来临时  鸟群回巢了
The birds return as dusk falls.
迄今  在与害虫们的竞赛中
So far, we're one step ahead
我们占了先手
in the arms race with the pests.
我们驾驭草原的能力
And our ability to manipulate the grasslands
也越来越强大了
has gone from strength to strength.
我们有这些超大型的人造草原
We have supersized these man-made grasslands...
改造群山  砍伐森林
...sculpting mountains, felling forests
重新设计我们星球的每块表面
and redesigning the very surface of our planet.
七块草地可以养活几乎七十亿人
Seven grasses feed almost seven billion people.
它们供给我们所需糖类的四分之三
They supply three-quarters of our carbohydrates,
还有面包和意面  面条和粥
bread and pasta, noodles and porridge.
这些人造大平原正在制造野生草原
These artificial great plains are making wild grasslands
其中有地球上濒危的栖息地
amongst the most endangered habitats on Earth.
然而正是在这养育了
Yet it was on the wild grasslands,
大量畜牧的野生草原上
which support vast grazing herds,
我们获得了或许是最大的成功
that we achieved perhaps our greatest triumph...
按照我们的需要征服了这些动物
to subjugate these animals to our needs.
控制一种植物是一回事
Controlling a plant is one thing,
但要支配一种动物并符合其自由意愿
but dominating a creature with its own free will
则需要更高水准的驾驭能力
requires a far higher level of manipulation.
蒙古大草原是地球上最大的草原
The Mongolian steppe is the biggest grassland on Earth.
在这里奔跑着
There are more horses running wild here
世界上最多的马
than anywhere else in the world.
蒙古人高超的驯马能力
The Mongols' ability to tame horses
让这些游牧民成了大草原的主宰
has made these nomads masters of the steppe.
在一个牧马家庭里
And, in a family of horsemen,
乌拉纳是最出色的
Ulaana is the best.
他的骑术是流淌在血液里的
He's got riding in his blood.
他的祖先成吉思汗
His ancestor Genghis Khan
用马的力量建立起了一个帝国
used horse power to build an empire,
但今天
but today,
乌拉纳的家族面临着一个不同的挑战
Ulaana's family face a different challenge.
他们必须利用马的速度
They must use their horses' speed
和耐力去捕捉野生母马
and stamina to capture wild mares.
把野马群赶回蒙古包
Driving the wild herd back
只是一天的开始
to the ger camp is only the beginning of a day
乌拉纳敏捷和力量的极限将受到考验
that will test Ulaana's agility and strength to the limit.
我骑马的时候觉得很有活力
他的终极目标是马奶
Ultimately he's after the mare's milk,
但这并不容易
but it's not that straightforward.
这些野母马不会轻易地交出奶水
These wild mares don't give up their milk easily.
只有通过诱骗它们才行
They have to be tricked into it.
他的成功将取决于
His success will depend on
他与胯下的马能否默契配合
total partnership with his horse.
一匹善于追逐的马会知道我的目标
并紧紧跟在那匹马后
首先  乌拉纳要用套索套住小马驹
First, Ulaana lassoes the foals,
这样母马们就不会跑远
so the mares will stay close.
不过就算是小马驹也很倔强
But even the foals are feisty.
乌拉纳斜胯在马的一侧
Ulaana leans behind his horse,
利用它的力量和体重
using its strength and weight
来抵挡小马驹的牵拉
to resist the pull of the foal.
他必须在疾驰中
He must balance at a gallop,
仅靠双膝来保持平衡
using only his knees.
一旦他抓到一头小马
Once he's caught a foal,
他的表姐妹唐加立即给它戴上笼头
his cousin Tungaa must get a halter on
以防逃脱
before it escapes.
这是野马们第一次感受到人类的抚摸
It is the first time they have felt the touch of a human hand.
小马一旦被拴起来
Once they're tethered,
乌拉纳就可以追捕那些母马了
Ulaana can move on to the mares.
这时才是真正的战斗
This is the real battle -
母马的体重是他的五倍
mares are five times his weight.
给它逃走了  居然没抓住
不行  一头都捉不住
它们很善于逃出套索
古拉纳倾尽全力的同时
With Ulaana at full stretch,
大家也都伸出了援手
everyone lends a hand.
在几近精疲力尽的两小时后
After two exhausting hours,
人类终于开始占了上风
the men begin to get the upper hand.
这头母马被套上缰绳  腿也被捆了起来
Haltered and hobbled,
终于屈服了
this mare is finally subdued.
之后他们将小马驹还给它  以稳定情绪
Then they're left to calm down with their foals.
只有给小马喂奶时  母马才会释放乳汁
Only with the foal suckling will the mare let down her milk
这时唐加才能乘隙而入
and then Tungaa has a brief chance
为家里挤点马奶
to draw some off for the family.
不过蒙古人更喜欢再做些加工
But Mongolians prefer their milk with a twist.
他们的创新之处就在于
Their innovation has been to ferment
将这种甜甜的马奶发酵成奶酒
this sugary milk into airag,
就是一种含有少量酒精的酸奶
a slightly alcoholic yoghurt.
接下来换你来搅拌  然后换你  轮流来
乳酸菌把牛奶发酵成了
The yoghurt bacteria turns the milk
他们最有营养的夏日美味
into their most nutritious summer food.
搅拌得越多越好
这样才能做出新鲜冒泡的奶酒
你喝起来就像那些渴死的奶牛
只要不伤害这些动物
Without harming their animals,
乌拉纳家可以年年依赖它们
Ulaana's family can live off them year after year,
把野草转变成酸奶
turning the goodness of grass into yoghurt
但作为生活与食草牧群紧密相连的
but, having bound their lives to the grazing herds,
游牧民族
they are nomads,
他们要一直跟着牧群
following the herds on their perpetual search
不断寻找新的牧场
for fresh pastures.
动物们知道如何寻找到最肥美的草
这是它们的本能
所以我们就跟随它们的脚步
在其他文明中
In other cultures,
这种对于牧群的驾驭又上了一个台阶
we have taken this mastery a step further,
我们可以驯服并培育野生牧群
taming and breeding the wild herds,
让它们更加易于掌控
making them docile and easy to handle.
在非洲的大草原
In the African savannah,
牧民们把牛群看得很紧
herders keep their cattle close.
它们已经有了主人
They are owned now
和所有的私人财产一样
and, like property owners everywhere,
主人们会为保卫资产而战
men will fight to protect them.
在埃塞俄比亚南部的草原上
In the grasslands of southern Ethiopia,
苏里族人将这种捍卫表现到了极致
the Suri take this protection to extremes.
部落间甚至会为了牛群而大动干戈
Here, rival tribes even fight battles over cattle.
所以苏里族人必须个个都是战士
So Suri herders must become warriors.
为了捍卫自己的牲口
Shahuri will stop at nothing
希哈里可以不惜一切
to defend his herd.
我会为了我的牛群奋战到死
牛群就是我的全部
从儿时起就是这样了
在苏里族中  牛是通用货币
For the Suri, cattle are currency.
太贵重了  他们是不舍得屠宰的
Too valuable to kill,
而是尽心尽力地照顾它们
they care for them intimately.
我们给牛群生火取暖
每年希哈里都要参加一项传统的争勇比赛
Every year Shahuri must undergo a ritual trial of courage
来证明他够格当一名牛群斗士
to prove he's got what it takes to be a cattle warrior.
他直接饮用
He gets strength for the combat
自己奶牛身上的血
ahead directly from his cows
来获得格斗的力量
by drinking their blood.
也许这看起来有些残忍
It may look brutal,
但还不至于伤牛性命
but it doesn't kill them.
这些营养丰富的血液提供了希哈里
This rich blood gives Shahuri
很多重要的蛋白质和铁元素
essential protein and iron,
他那头珍贵的母牛也会很快康复
and his prize animal will recover quickly.
喝生血会让我们更强壮
这场名叫"当加"的传统比赛
The vicious ritual of Donga
对希哈里的牛仔声名而言
will make or break
成败就在此一举
Shahuri's reputation as a cowboy.
审判之日终于来临
It's the day of judgment.
几支苏里族的竞争部落
The rival Suri clans arrive,
兴奋地抵达赛场  各就各位
psyched up and ready for Donga.
这场竞赛要持续一天
It lasts a day.
你从邻村人中
You pick an opponent
选择一名对手对决
from the neighbouring village for a duel.
赢得的场次越多
The more victories you win,
就越能彰显你的勇气
the greater your courage.
希哈里走进格斗场地
Shahuri walks to the ring.
敢来参加比赛就已经要很大勇气了
Even taking part in this ritual takes serious guts.
而他甚至都没戴护甲
He has no armour.
仅有的防护就是他的幸运遮阳帽
His only defence is a lucky sunhat.
希哈里静候时机
Shahuri watches and waits.
"当加"比赛中的棍子长达两米
The Donga sticks are two metres long.
能引起严重的损伤
They can cause serious injury.
要赢的话
To win,
你必须连续抽打你的对手
you must thrash your opponent
直到他投降
until surrender.
终于  希哈里准备上场了
Finally, Shahuri is ready for battle.
他赢了  但说服力还不够
It's a victory, but not emphatic.
为了证明自己  他再次上场
To prove himself, he fights again.
突然他的对手退下场去
Suddenly his opponent backs down.
希哈里是最后的赢家
Shahuri is the champion.
他的同族们将他高高举起  庆祝胜利
Lifted high, his clan celebrate his victory.
我在"当加"比赛中非常英勇
在捍卫我的牛群时也很英勇
他的牛群终于有了守卫者
His cattle have their protector.
希哈里证明了自己是个够格的
Shahuri has proved he can be a cowboy,
"埃塞俄比亚牛仔"
Ethiopian style.
然而  在澳大利亚内陆
But in the Australian outback,
人们重新诠释了牛仔的含义
they've reinvented the cowboy big time.
这里的超级大农场
Here, supersized ranches
横跨全国  拥有三千多万头牛
across the country hold 30 million cattle.
这是人类对野兽彻彻底底的征服
This is the total mastery of man over beast,
体现了我们在草原上聪敏巧思的极致
our ultimate ingenuity in the grasslands.
在这里转上一圈曾经要一个月
Round-up used to take a month.
现在不会了
Not any more.
本・塔普是牧群领航员
Ben Tapp is a muster pilot,
他必须在五天内把他最好的
and he must bring in 2,000 of
两千头牛赶去卖掉
his best cattle in just five days to get paid.
他必须运用他所有的飞行技巧
He'll need all his flying skills,
以及读懂牛群心思的能力
his ability to read the cattle,
还有同伴兰金的帮助才能成功
and his mate Rankin, if he's to succeed.
如果你能理解牛群
If you can understand the cattle,
你就能预料到它们的动向
you can already anticipate what they're going to do.
如同一个优秀的牧牛人
Like a good cattleman,
你能认出每一头牛
you can identify every single beast,
每一头都不一样
and every single beast is different.
他的牛群就在不远处
His cattle are out there somewhere.
在空中侦察可以让本迅速定位
Scouting by air allows Ben to home in on them fast.
这条线上大概有六到七头牛
It appears there's about six or seven of them along the line.
当他们找到牛群时
When they find a group of cows,
他们会降低到"死亡高度"
they drop down to the "Death zone"
将它们驱赶出来
to flush them out.
只要刮到树木都将是致命的
Clipping any tree will be fatal.
别逼得太紧
Don't put too much pressure on them.
它们现在很紧张
They're fairly hot now.
跟紧那头掉队的就行
Just stick with that mob there.
让它们继续这样走
Keep them going that way.
你来跟紧它们  坏小子在这里
You stick with them. Oh, here's this mob here.
总是有那么些制造麻烦的牛
There are always some trouble-makers.
我们又有大概150头牛加入行列
We've got another...probably 150 coming in.
摩托车也一同工作  帮助驱赶牛群
The choppers work together, pushing the growing herd,
不过他们还有五十公里要走
but they've got 50 kilometres and billabongs
在到达农场前  还要横渡洼地
to cross before they get to the ranch.
本的牛群实在不太喜欢游泳
Ben's cattle really don't like swimming.
只要它们准备好下水  无论哪里
Anywhere here, where they're ready to cross,
我们都直接让它们过河
we'll just let them go.
当心了
Oh, look out, look out!
每年都有约十名领航员坠地着火丧生
Every year, about ten muster pilots crash and burn.
稳住了
Just steady up there.
-它们正往前走  -是的
- They just work along... - Yeah.
还剩八公里时
From eight kilometres out,
地面人员也加入了驱赶的队伍
the ground crew joins the drive.
我想我们应该往南偏一点
I think we'll target a little bit southward.
往这边来  都到齐了吗
Come around. Everyone's here, right?
本还在发号施令
But Ben's still calling the shots.
摩托车跟上
Oh, the motorbike follows. Come on!
快点  摩托车赶快跟上
Come on, motorbike! Motorbike follow, come on!
快点  它们要往那边去了
Hurry up! They're going to go that way!
让它们继续保持这个方向前进
Keep them going the way they are heading there now.
如今  我们再也不用等待
Now, we don't need to wait
动物们的自然迁徙了
for the wildebeest migration,
我们可以自己创造
we create our own.
草原使得我们可以主宰这个星球
Grasslands have allowed us to dominate the planet.
它们是人类勾勒出的
They are the landscape
美好的画卷
of phenomenal human achievement.
巩固了我们现在整体生存的状态
They underpin our present global existence.
这些牛群  生在印度  长在澳大利亚
These cattle, native to India, raised in Australia,
很快就会被运往全球各地
will soon be shipped out
满足各国对于牛肉的需求
to feed the international appetite for beef.
牧牛季过去后
And over the season...
它们会让本成为百万富翁
they'll make Ben a millionaire.
-你靠这些赚了不少钱吧  -是的
- Are you making much out of it? - Yeah.
大概有130万美金
About 1.3 million bucks.
为此整日操劳还是挺值的嘛
That's worth getting out of bed for!
没错
Yeah.
我们的匠心巧工  团队精神
Our ingenuity and teamwork,
还有无畏的勇气
intelligence and courage
都在草原上得到了充分的发扬光大
have all been refined in the grasslands.
正是这些人类独有的能力
And this uniquely human combination of skills
让我们征服了世界
has enabled us to conquer the world.
如果没有这些草原
Without the grasslands,
地球永远就不可能成为人类的地球
planet Earth would never have become the Human Planet.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
要从非洲最凶猛的猎食者囊中
Trying to steal food from the
苟且地偷得一些食物
jaws of the most powerful predator in Africa
听起来像异想天开
may seem to us like lunacy,
但这项特别且危险的举动
but this extraordinary and dangerous feat
却在肯尼亚有着几千年的历史
has been practised in Kenya for thousands of years.
但是关于它的影像纪录前无古人
But it has never been filmed before,
可能也不再会有来者
and may never be filmed again.
多罗博族是一个
The Dorobo are an ancient tribe
生活在东非草原的古老部落
who live in the grasslands of East Africa.
欧金耶  肯尼亚
现在的草原保护法禁止了
Conservation laws now stop
他们的很多传统活动
many of their traditional practices
因此大大威胁到他们的生存
and so threaten their whole way of life.
为了纪录这个独特的事件
To record this unique sequence,
草原拍摄组需要找到一个人
the Grasslands team needed a man
要既懂狮子的习性又了解当地的多罗博人
who understands both lions and the Dorobo people who live here.
摄影组的导游杰克逊・卢赛亚
Jackson Looseyia, the crew's guide,
对这种生活方式有着深刻的理解
has a deep understanding of this way of life,
从小生长在附近的马塞马拉地区
having grown up nearby in the Masai Mara.
BBC剧组问我
When I was asked by the BBC
他们能否纪录这个故事时
if they are able to document this story,
我说  能啊  我就亲自干过那事
I said, yeah, because it's something that I've practised myself.
我成长过程中经常追赶狮子来夺取食物
I've chased lions from food when I was growing up.
我了解这种生活方式
I knew this lifestyle.
杰克逊・卢赛亚
导游
是完全可能的
It's possible,
只要BBC剧组手脚够快
it's just a matter of if the BBC are able to capture
就能抓拍到好东西
this before it is gone.
但肯定不容易
It won't be easy,
这里的狮子对车很陌生
as the lions here aren't used to cars,
所以很难接近
so they're difficult to approach.
它们一般在夜晚出没猎食
They mainly hunt at night
徒步接近的话太危险
when it's too dangerous to get close on foot.
难就难在如何找到拂晓捕猎的狮子
So the challenge is to find a lion kill at dawn,
从而让多罗博人
to enable the Dorobo
和摄影师华伦・塞缪尔能完成拍摄
and big cat cameraman Warren Samuels to do their jobs.
我们得坐等狮子来猎食
We've got to wait for the lion to make the kill
那个时机必须刚好
and it's got to be at a time
华伦・塞缪尔
摄影师
既要能保证安全
when we can still come out early morning
又要有足够的自然光把片子拍好
and still have enough light to film them on the kill.
我们很期待能有好运气
We're hoping for a lot of luck.
第一缕光出现时  杰克逊加入了多罗博人
At first light, Jackson joins the Dorobo,
希望追踪一次鲜活的捕猎活动
in the hope of tracking down a fresh lion kill.
你看  这就是狮子的脚印
You can see this is a footprint of a lion,
看得出这狮子很大
a very big lion,
还有  这个脚印是羚羊的
and you can see there's a footprint of a wildebeest.
瞧啊  这是一个非常大的狮群
Look here, you see, this is a very, very big pride,
看看足印的数量
looking at the number of footprints,
还有常常喜欢来喝水的地方
and the number of places that they like to drink.
狮子喜欢在破晓之时捕猎
Because lions often hunt just before dawn,
所以摄影组只好不分昼夜地守着
the team have to follow them both day and night.
在非洲  夜晚有着数不尽的故事
In Africa, night is everything.
恐怖  可怕  但却充满生机
It's terrifying, it's scary. But it's so much alive.
杰克逊・卢赛亚
导游
看见它们了吗  那就是狮群
Do you see them? There are the lions,
我们找到了  仔细听
we've found them, listen.
和杰克逊一起值夜班的
Sharing the night shift with Jackson
是《人类星球》的学者  简・阿金斯
is Human Planet researcher, Jane Atkins.
我们遇到的是母狮和它们的八只小崽
We just came across lionesses with their eight cubs
对多罗博人居住的地区很熟络的样子
quite local to where the Dorobo guys live.
但是弊端在于
But the down side of that
简・阿金斯
《人类星球》的学者
当多罗博人目睹一次猎食行为时
is that when the Dorobo do come across a kill,
特别是狮群又在主场作战
if it's in this area with this pride,
这些母狮子们
these lionesses are going to be
会被激发起更强的攻击性和保护欲
a lot more aggressive and protective.
在夜晚努力想跟上这个狮群很是困难
The struggle to try and keep up with this pride at night
他们聚集在那边
is because they cross in places
机动车没法过去
that a vehicle would not be able to cross.
一旦跟丢了
Once you lose them, you know,
你就可能会错过它们的猎食行为
they do stuff behind your back.
所以得时刻紧紧跟着
So you are having to be on the go the whole time.
跟踪了狮群整整一晚
After following the lions all night,
他们还是未能看到狮子的猎食
they still haven't seen a kill.
值白班的华伦
Warren, on the day shift,
发现了其中的原因
discovers there's a very good reason why.
最理想的情况是
Ideally, the situation
有一大群羚羊供捕杀
we wanted here was big herds of wildebeest,
然后狮子大量地捕杀它们
we wanted to get lions making kills,
但是今年雨季来的有点早
but the rains have come a little early,
大部分的动物都迁徙到平原了
so most of the animals are up on the plains.
所以现在能见到的都是五六只的小群羚羊
All we've got now are small groups of five or six wildebeest.
我们非常希望
So we're really hoping
有一个狮群能幸运地遇到
that one of those groups of lions gets lucky
并且杀死其中一头羚羊
and that they manage to kill one of them.
没有别的羚羊群了
No more groups of wildebeest.
唯一一群就在你眼前
Just that one group you can see.
又过了四天
Four more days pass
还是没有目睹狮子猎杀羚羊
and no lion kills have been seen.
终于  他们走了一点点小运
Finally, they get a shred of luck.
目前有一大群羚羊
We've got a big herd of wildebeest
从地平线那头迁徙回来
going through the horizon heading to the crossings again.
我们有机会等到一次狮子的捕杀
We may have a chance again of a kill.
摄制组立刻跟上多罗博人的脚步
The crew head off on the heels of the Dorobo.
几小时的追随过后
But after hours of tracking,
还是未有狮子捕杀的迹象
again there's no sign of a kill.
又轮到简和夜巡组了
Jane and the night shift take over.
我们发现了正在觅食的一头母狮
We've just come across the lionesses
一头公狮  还有小崽们
and the male and all their cubs on a kill,
我们只有
and we are about...
大概五米远
five metres away.
那头公狮正在捕杀羚羊
The adult male is sitting now on a wildebeest kill.
我们现在还不能拍
We are not going to be able to film this
因为  等天亮的时候
because, by the time it gets light,
它们早就完成了
they'll have finished it.
但能如此近距离地观察真是让人惊奇
But it's absolutely amazing to be able to see it so close.
摄制组的车被23头饥饿的狮子包围
The vehicle is now surrounded by 23 hungry lions.
那是什么  就在车门外
天啊
Oh, God!
天哪
My God!
刚刚有一头狮子
We've just had a lion
在嚼我们的备用胎
chewing at our back tyre,
我着实吓了一跳
and I absolutely kacked myself!
打死我也不敢走上前去
或者偷走它们的食物
瞅瞅那模样
Look at them!
多罗博人可不这么想
Not the Dorobo.
他们一直都这样
They say they do it all the time.
我不知道他们怎么办到的
I don't know how they do it, I mean...
真的很可怕
...it's terrifying.
破晓时  狮群早已完成了猎杀
By dawn, the lions have finished the kill.
换班的时候  狮子的咬功才被发现
At the shift change, the power of the lion's bite is revealed.
看啊  真是不可思议
Look at that, it's amazing!
真是个亢奋的夜晚
Quite an adrenaline-filled night, really.
现在是早上八点  我刚值完夜班
It's eight in the morning, I've just finished my night shift,
尽管发现了在捕猎的狮群
and although we found lions on a kill,
等到华伦出来
by the time Warren came out
光线适合拍摄的时候
and it was light enough for him to film,
但羚羊的残骸已消失殆尽
the carcass was pretty much ripped apart.
我们只剩几天了
You know, we've only got a few more days left.
最后他们终于等到了好消息
At last they get the news everyone's been waiting for.
他们一直跟踪的那个狮群正在猎杀
The pride they've been following has made a fresh kill.
光线足够进行拍摄  多罗博人也蓄势待发
It's light enough to film, and the Dorobo are ready.
我们在物色一个绝佳之处
We are just trying to find a position
能够有一个清晰的视野
where we can get a clear view.
路上灌木丛太多了
There's too much brush in the way.
拍摄组还很担心多罗博人的安全
The crew are still worried about the Dorobos' safety.
它们可能会咬死我们
当你做这事时  你都想着他人而不是自己
你都想着他人而不是自己
摄制组这么担心我们
看起来是在劝我们放弃
好像我们是菜鸟一样
真不敢相信我们能拍到这个镜头
I didn't believe that we would get this shot.
我还以为狮子们会攻击他们
I thought the lions would attack these guys
尤其是当他们还要靠近小崽时
especially when they had their cubs.
突然  那只大公狮站起来开始跑
But all of a sudden, when the big male got up and ran,
我以为它是来攻击我们的
I was relieved, because I thought he would be
但它没有  一颗心就放下了
the one which will attack us,
但我真的很开心  好激动  哎呀呀
but I'm really, really chuffed. Great stuff! Ay-ay-ah!
我和多罗博人在生活方式上
The special connection I've got with the Dorobo
建立了一种特别的联系
is the lifestyle.
想到这种联系就要失去了让人很感伤
It's pretty sad to know that it's about to disappear.
和他们在一起的这段时间
The time that I've spent with these guys,
实在是过得太快了
I think it's too short.
我意识到我失去了什么
I've realised how much I have lost
也知道从和他们相处的两周里
and how much I have learnt so far
学到了什么
since I have been with them in the last two weeks.
我会很开心的
I would be very happy
要是这部片子可以留给我孩子们看
if this has been captured for my kids
留给多罗博人的子孙们看
and the rest of the generations of the Dorobo kids,
并且为我们的祖先  父辈  兄长们的
and be proud that our ancestors, our fathers, our elders
这些壮举而感到自豪
did practise this scary, scary experience.